<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A prognostication Buckminster 1591]</title>
            <author>Buckminster, Thomas, ca. 1531-1599?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17405</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 423.6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4489</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23434379</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23434379</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26623</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17405)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26623)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1826:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A prognostication Buckminster 1591]</title>
                  <author>Buckminster, Thomas, ca. 1531-1599?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Watkins and J. Roberts,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.p. lacking; running title.</note>
                  <note>Publishers suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: fragments.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Almanacs, English.</term>
               <term>Ephemerides.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26623:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26623:1"/>
            <head>Obſeruations to be vſed in letting of blood, purging, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and Sweating. &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Blood letting.</head>
               <p>LEt not Blood at any time without iuſt cauſe, for it bringeth weaknes, and many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities: and when it is to be done, let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be with due conſiderations, and the aduice of ſome learned Phiſition, ſo that it may be done (if neceſſitie enforce not the contrarie) after good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, and faſting, in a fayre temperate day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and beware of all maner of exceſſe, as labouring, watchyng, carnall copulation. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And theſe Signes generally are good to let Blood in, namely, <hi>Aries, Libra, Sagittarius,</hi> and <hi>Piſces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Perticulerly, for chollericke perſons, when the Moone is in <hi>Cancer, Scorpius,</hi> and <hi>Piſces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the flemmaticke in <hi>Aries</hi> &amp; <hi>Sagittarius</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26623:1"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es: and it is beſt comforted, when the Moone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in <hi>Aries, Leo,</hi> and <hi>Sagittarius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond is the vertue digeſtiue, ſo named, becauſe it digeſteth or altereth the noryſhment into a due forme. If it be too weake to do the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffice, it is beſt ſtrengthened when the Moone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in <hi>Gemini, Libra,</hi> and <hi>Aquarius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third is the vertue retentiue, and is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed ſo, becauſe it keepeth in the good noryſhment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>artyll the digeſtiue vertue hath duely digeſted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd changed it. It is chiefly holpen, the Moone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing in <hi>Taurus, Virgo,</hi> and <hi>Capricorne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth is called the vertue expulſiue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his office is to expell and put out thoſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous excrementes whiche remayne when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he other vertues haue done their offices duely. It is beſt relieued the Moone being in <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er, Scorpius,</hi> and <hi>Piſces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The vertue Attractiue is gouerned of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sunne. The vertue Digeſtiue is gouerned of <hi>Iupiter.</hi> The vertue Retentiue is gouerned of <hi>Saturne.</hi> The vertue Expulſiue is gouerned of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:26623:1"/>
               <head>Of the Eclipſes of this yeer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of our Lord. 1591.</head>
               <p>AS touching the Eclipſes in this yeer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which are three in number: that is to ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one of the Sunne happening the .x. day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Iuly, at two of the clocke and .xxvi. min. in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> after noone, beyng darkened but one poyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which is a very ſmall thyng, and of no gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſignification.</p>
               <p>And the ſeconde (which is the firſt of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Moone) is the .xxvi. day of Iuly, at .iiii. of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> clocke in the after noone alſo, and vnder o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Horizon, being yet darkened .xvii. poyntes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a halfe. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And the thirde, which is the ſeconde of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Moone, is the .xx. day of December at three <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the clocke, and .xx. min. in the mornyng, in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſigne. <hi>Cancer,</hi> &amp; wyll be darkened .xix. poyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and more in the .viii. houſe of the Heauens.</p>
               <p>Of theſe I ſay, in reſpect that one ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not be ſeene of vs at all, and another very lyt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and the thyrde, though it ſhalbe manifeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſeene, yet the effectes thereof ſhall not take pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26623:1"/>declares &amp; ſhewed in the perticuler iudgementes of the dayes of the monethes, conteyning this firſt quarter. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The diſtemperance of this quarter is lyke to breed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>any ſickneſſes, and ſundry diſeaſes, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ng folkes, as in old, as namely Agues of all fates, Stitches, grypinges, the Collicke, Surf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes, the Megrime, and ache in the Head and Shoulders, Pluriſies, ſmall Pockes, Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es in the Maw, Horſenes, Rewine, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Coughes, hardnes in fetching the breath the Strangurie, and ſuch others, payne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ffer, and not eaſie to cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Spring time.</head>
               <p>THe Spring taketh his beginning at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mes entring into the firſt min. of the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <hi>Aries,</hi> which ſhalbe on Thurſeday the .x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of March, at .iii. of the clocke and .xvi. min. in the after noone, making the day &amp; nyght to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne length through the whole worlde.</p>
               <p>The quarter of the yeere is naturally hot and moyſt temperately, and is therfore reckoned the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lſome tyme in the yeere, and it is now the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tyme to remoue ſickneſſes, and griefes
<pb facs="tcp:26623:1"/>gotten before, and alſo to preuent thoſe to come: for if the body of man do abounde with humors, which are ready to oppreſſe nature, whether there be preſent ſicknes by the meanes of them, or els danger of ſicknes to come: thoſe humors are beſt to be emptied out of the body nowe, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by lettyng of blood, purging, hathyng, ſweating, or ſuch lyke euacuation, which at this tyme I wyll not proſecute.</p>
               <p>The diſpoſition of the weather in this quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the yeere, is lyke to be very variable and inconſtant: for as there are lyke to be many hot and dry dayes, ſhewyng a great l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>clynes of continuance: ſo on the contrary there wylbe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſhewers tempered with the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry clappes of thunder and lyghtninges, making the weather vncertayne, with cloudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered heate, and moyſtnes.</p>
               <p>The ſickneſſes lyke to be in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, are Feuers of long continuance, Fluxes of the belly, the faſlyng ſicknes, rotten coughes, thinne rewines, the head ache, plureſies, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tre impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumes in the breſtes and ſydes, Stitches, Crampes, payne in the necke and br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, with dyuers others, both noyſome and alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nous.
<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26623:1"/>moſt part ſtormie, and very colde, with great inconſtantie, as cloudy ſometime, and thycke darke weather: at other tymes fierce raines by ſhewers, &amp; often dryuing wyndes, with ſnow or fleete myrt with rayne. At other times thunder, with rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſuch lyke diſtempered weather.</p>
               <p>It is to be feared that nowe ſome ſtrange ſickneſſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and vnknowen diſeaſes ſhall happen, and be heard of among the people, and alſo bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s, inflammation of the Lunges, paſſions of the Hart, obſtructions in the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uer, weakenes in the Backe, ſwellyng and hardnes in the Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ent, Rewines, Catharres, watery F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ures, and ſuch lyke, both dangerous &amp; deadly.</p>
               <p>God of his great mercy turne from vs all thoſe euylles which are entended againſt vs, and geue vs grace to amende our wicked lyues, the procuring cauſes of all our puniſhmentes, and let vs firſt be carefull for our ſoules, as for our
<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26623:1"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deane contrarie: As firſt, to ſtudy for good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, next for health, and laſt for wealth for yf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> firſt ſeeke the kingdome of God, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>ouſnes thereof, the other things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>albe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iniſtred vnto vs. But we ſee by ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at is too common, ſo great blindnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong men, that they care in ſuch wiſe for ryches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ely, that in reſpect thereof, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lytle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r health of the body, and nothing at all for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood eſtate and proſperitie of the ſoule, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt lamentable and ſorowfull.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>A note of the names and natures of ſome of the Windes, and what ſyck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes they breede and bring.</head>
            <p>The eaſt Wind called Subſolan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> being
<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26623:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>colde rayne, and enclined to thunder. The .xiiii. day, colde and inconſtant. The .xv. and .xvi. dayes, mylder weather then before. The .xvii. and .xviii. dayes, waueryng, and lowryng cold. The .xix. day, freſh ayre.</p>
            <p>The firſt quarter on Saterday, the .xx. day, at .viii. of the clocke, and .xi. min. in the morning, moyſt weather, and colde. The .xxi. and .xxii. dayes, freſh wyndes, and raw cold. The .xxiii. and .xxiiii. dayes, ſome rayne. The .xxv. and xxvi. dayes, temperate for this tyme. The .xxvii. day, colde and ſomewhat wyndy.</p>
            <p>The full Moone on Sunday, the .xxviii. day, at .iiii. of the clocke in the morning, cloſe and colde, the wynd ſomewhat Northerly.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of March.</head>
               <p>THe firſt and ſecond dayes, colde and foule weather. The .iii. and .iiii. dayes, colde, but not ſo foule as before. The .v. and .vi. dayes, ſhewery. The .vii. more temperate.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26623:3"/>
               <p>noone, ſome moyſture threatned. The .xxix. and xxx. dayes, fayre for the tyme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of May.</head>
               <p>THe firſt and ſeconde dayes, colde ayre, and variable cloudes. The .iii. and .iiii. dayes, lowryng and cloſe weather. The .v. day, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me ſmall rayne.</p>
               <p>The laſt quarter on Thurſeday, the .vi. day, at .v. of the clocke and .xiiii. min. in the mornyng, freſh weather, the wynde Northweſt. The .vii. and .viii. dayes, colde &amp; moyſt weather. The .ix. and .x. dayes, very temperate. The .xi. day, much lyke the two former.</p>
               <p>The new Moone on Wedneſday, the .xii. day, at .vii. of the clocke, and .xxix. min. in the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, wynd &amp; rayne. The .xiii. and .xiiii. dayes, variable. The .xv. and .xvi. dayes, cloudy and moyſt weather. The .xvii. xviii. and .xix. dayes, gloomy weather, with ſome ſhewers.</p>
               <p>The firſt quarter on Thurſeday, the .xx. day, at one of the clocke, and .iii. min. in the mornyng, wyndy &amp; cloudy, weſterly wyndes threatnyng rayne. The .xxi. &amp; .xxii. dayes, rayne. The .xxiii.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26623:3"/>
               <head>Of September.</head>
               <p>THe .i. and .ii. dayes, temperate and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng. The .iii. and .iiii. dayes, rayne and wynde. The .v. and .vi. dayes, variable and lyke to thunder.</p>
               <p>The new Moone on Tueſday, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> day, at .v. of the clocke in the after noone, ſomewhat freſhe, but dry, the wynd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> towarde the north. The .viii. and .ix. dayes, wyndy, with ſome ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers. The .x. day, fayre. The .xi. and .<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i. dayes, vnſetled weather. The .xiii. and .x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. dayes, wyndy and waueryng.</p>
               <p>The firſt quarter on Wedneſday the .xv. day, at .ix. of the clocke in the nyght, nyſſyng rayne and wynd. The .xvi. xvii. and .xv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i. dayes, boyſterous &amp; lowryng weather. The .xix. xx. and .xxi. dayes, more mylde then the former.</p>
               <p>The full Moone on Wedneſday, the .xxii. day, at .ix. of the clocke, and .xi. min. in the nyght, temperate weather, the wynde eaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. The .xxiii. and .xxiiii. dayes, ſome raine falle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is wyndy. The .xxv. xxvi. and .xx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. dayes cloudy cloſe, with rayne and cold. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> .xxviii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day, cold ayre toward euenyng.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26623:2"/>
               <p>and xxiiii dayes, very ſeaſonable. The .xxv. and xxvi. dayes, ſomewhat wyndy and ouercaſt, yet holdyng vp.</p>
               <p>The la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t quarter on Saterday, the .xxvii. day, at .vi. of the clocke, and .xxv. min. in the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me ſmall froſt toward. The .xxviii. day, ſomewhat lowryng &amp; thycke cloudes. The . xxix. and .xxx. dayes, cold ayre, and ouercaſt wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her for ſnow or thicke rayne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of December.</head>
               <p>THe .i. and .ii. dayes, darke or thicke ayre, as it would ſnow. The .iii. and .iiii. dayes, wyndy and foule.</p>
               <p>The new Moone on Sunday, the .v. day, at x. of the clocke and .xxv. min. at nyght, cold and wyndy. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> .vi. day, rayne and cold blaſtes. The .vii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> .vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. dayes, cold and dry. The .ix. and x. dayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate &amp; ſeaſonable for this tyme. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> dayes, wynd and cold raynes.</p>
               <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>arter on Munday, the .xiii. day, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and .xxviii. min. before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
